<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A horrible creuel and bloudy murther committed at Putney in Surrey on the 21. of Aprill last, 1614, being thursday, vpon the body of Edward Hall a miller of the same parish, done by the hands of Iohn Selling, Peeter Pet and Edward Streater, his seruants to the said Hall, each of them giuing him a deadly blow (as he lay sleeping) with a pickax. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117608</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 839:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A horrible creuel and bloudy murther committed at Putney in Surrey on the 21. of Aprill last, 1614, being thursday, vpon the body of Edward Hall a miller of the same parish, done by the hands of Iohn Selling, Peeter Pet and Edward Streater, his seruants to the said Hall, each of them giuing him a deadly blow (as he lay sleeping) with a pickax. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>I. T., fl. 1614, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By G. Eld] for Iohn Wright, and are to be sold without Newgate at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: I.T.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-A1,B4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hall, Edward, d. 1614 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Horrible Creuel and bloudy Murther,</hi> Committed at Putney in Surrey on the 21. of
<hi>Aprill laſt,</hi> 1614, <hi>being thurſday, vpon the body of</hi> Edward Hall <hi>a Miller of the ſame pariſh,</hi> Done by the hands of <hi>Iohn Selling, Peeter Pet</hi> and <hi>Edward Streater,</hi> his ſeruants to the ſaid <hi>Hall,</hi> each of them giuing <hi>him a deably blow (as he lay ſleeping) with a Pickax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a man holding an axe, and accompanied by another man and a demon, attacking from behind another, seated man.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> and are to be ſold without Newgate at the ſigue of the Bible. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader I do heere preſent vnto thy view one of the moſt horrible inhumane and bloody murthers that hath euer beene committed; which as it was damnably deuiſed ſo it was deuiliſhly and butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſhed and executed, whereby thou, and all the world may perceiue in what a miſerable eſtate the times are wherein we liue, when the thirſt and luker of a little cankered coyne, (with the inticements of the Deuil) ſhall haue ſuch predominance ouer the faculties of the minds of wretched men, that they will not ſtick to runne into moſt deſperate and dangerous actions, to the hazarding of ſoule and body, and to the finall temporall detriment of thoſe (their parents or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) whome they are in duty bound to loue, honour and reuerence then let this diſcourſe bee vnto thee as an Epitomy or breife abſtract (to thee) of the miſeries of man, and the illuſions of Sathan; in reading of which if thou haſt a remorce or feeling of the want of grace in men, then pray to him that is the giuer of grace, that hee may be graciouſly pleaſed to make the vngratious world more gracious.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Farwel,</hi> I. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:3"/>
            <head>A HORRIBLE CRVELL AND bloudy Murther, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted at <hi>Putney</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> on the one and twentieh of <hi>Aprill laſt</hi> 1614.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS old impotent decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit age wherein wee liue, the doating World lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping on hir laſt legges, whereas impieties, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, iniquities, vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, and thouſandes more of hell-hatched enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities haue gotten the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per per hand, where the ſweet ſeeming baytes of Sathan leades men (like beares by the noſes) to commit all horrid and damnable
<pb facs="tcp:18171:4"/>treſpaſſes, and tranſgreſſions againſt the Deuine Maieſtie of the omnipotent and eternall God. By which abhominations the wrath of the moſt high is oftentimes iuſtly kindled againſt miſerable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouernd mankinde. So that God in his iuſtice giues many ouer to a reprobate ſence, that they haue no remorce or feeling of the breach or viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſacred lawes of their immortall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and ſo (woe worth the while) As they liue diſſolutely, they dye deſperatly, and after all (that which is worſt) they liue a dying life eternally, or dye a liuing death euerlaſtingly. What num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of execrable and inhumane murthers are day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed by barbarous, and brutiſh minded men, on the bodies of their brethren, that <hi>Caine</hi> who was the firſt of that bloudy fraternitie, if hee were on the earth would bluſh to heare and ſee how farre he is out paſſed in butcheries? Amongſt the number of numberleſſe bloud-thirſty pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irides and homicides: let this, which is heere following treated of, bee accounted and Recorded for none of the leaſt which was effected, accompliſhed, and reuealed in this ſort. In the Pariſh of <hi>Putney</hi> vpon Thames in the Countie of <hi>Surrey,</hi> fiue or ſixe miles diſtant from the Cittie of London, there dwelt this Murdered Man, named
<hi>Edward Hall,</hi> by his vocation a Miller, a man of good r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>putati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hauing ſubſtance of money and moueables ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient: now this aforeſaid <hi>Hall</hi> (notwithſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng his ſufficiency of all things needefull, yet his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination was to bee ſparing, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner miſerable in his howſe-keeping, which procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him the hatred of his ſeruants and familie,
<pb facs="tcp:18171:4"/>and in concluſion was a great mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e deſtruction; for it is Reported that his wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bigge with Child, and that his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed the time of her deliuerance to draw neere, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e charges of hir lying in, did ſend his th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e miles into the Countrie to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mothers, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e meane ſpace in hir abſence, hee was thus trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly, and inhumainly maſſacred and Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; for vpon Thurſday night the one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt <hi>1614.</hi> about tenne of the clock after ſupper, the ſaid <hi>Hall</hi> ſleeping in a Chaire by the fire in his Kitchin, his ſeruants (beeing three of them) namely <hi>Iohn Selling, Peter Pett,</hi> and <hi>Edward Streater,</hi> hauing (as they confeſſed) conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Maſter his death long before, now they perceiued him ſleeping, thought it not fitte to let ſuch an opportunitie ſlip to put their damnable practiſe in execution. <hi>Iohn Selling</hi> hauing proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a pickaxe to giue the fatall blow, told the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid <hi>Pett</hi> that now it was a fitte time to doe it, and bade <hi>Pett</hi> ſtrike the firſt ſtroake, and hee would ſecond him with another: whereupon <hi>Pett</hi> tooke the pickaxe, and ſtanding behinde his ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Maiſter, lifting it vp with all his force (bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrengthened by the inſpiration of the Deuill, who was a Murtherer from the beginning) gaue his Maſter a violent blow on the back betwixt his ſhoulders, wherewith <hi>Hall</hi> beeing aſtonnied fell downe and gaue a great groane, where
<hi>Selling</hi> preſently catcht the pickaxe out of <hi>Pette</hi> handes ſtroake the ſecond blow at <hi>Hall,</hi> and hitting him on the head, in moſt cruell and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ly manner,
<pb facs="tcp:18171:5"/>beate out his braines, the other (their third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in this miſchiefe) named <hi>Streater,</hi> being all this while grinding corne in his Maiſters Mill, a little diſtant from the houſe, not knowing as then that the deuiliſh deſigne was acompliſhed, till at laſt <hi>Pett</hi> went to him and told him what was done, and bade him come and beholde their handy-worke: preſently vpon this <hi>Streater</hi> left the Mill, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the houſe where hee ſaw his ſaid Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter lye imbrued in his owne gore, with his braines moſt brutiſhly daſht out. Hee vpon the inſtant, and imporunate requeſt or command of <hi>Pett</hi> &amp; <hi>Selling,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Streater</hi> tooke the pickaxe and ſtroke the ſaid <hi>Hall</hi> a blow on the breaſt which ſplit and ſhiuered his breaſt boane, <hi>Hall</hi> beeing thus dead, théſe three Murtherers conſulted amongſt themſelues what were beſt to bee done with the dead body, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and vowing that whoſoeuer ſhould reucale this their damnable deede, ſhould haue his braines beaten out. Then they all tooke vp the dead carkas and caried it into a Stable, where they digged a hole and buried it. And afterwards deuiſing what were the beſt courſe for them to take to keepe this murther concealed, and to kepe themſelues cleare from ſuſpition thereof, at laſt they bethought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of a gelding which was their Maiſters (at that time ſtanding in the ſtable) which gelding they (all three) tooke and ſadled and bridled, and led him forth the ſame night into <hi>Wimbleton</hi> wood where they turned the Horſe aſtray, looſly to wander vp and downe, that it might be thought that Theeues and robbers had aſſanited their aforeſaid Maiſter in the
<pb facs="tcp:18171:5"/>wood, or that ſome miſchance had there befalne him, of the which (as they imagined) the ſtraying Horſe would bee a manifeſt infalliable token: but (as I ſaid before) theſe villaines hauing thus turned the horſe looſe, returned home to their Maiſters houſe, where they ſearched, ſought, and ranſacked for mony, and at laſt they found the ſumme of betweene thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and fortie poundes, which was the accurſed wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and pillage which theſe Murderers got for their inhumaine and hortible execution of the death of their Maiſter, which by the iuſt iudgement of God they enioyed not long, for notwithſtanding that they had time to prouide for their ſafety, from the Thurſday night (wherein they did this murther) yet they remained there till Thurſday following, till it pleaſed the Lord that this bloudie fact was reuealed, which fell out in this ſort following. <hi>Hall</hi> was miſſed amongſt his neighbours, and it was giuen out, and reported by his ſeruants afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that hee was gone a farre iourney into the Countrie, but <hi>Edward Streater</hi> beeing further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, vpon his examination confeſſed vnto the Officers and chiefe men of the Pariſh of
<hi>Putney</hi> aboueſaid, the whole order and manner of their deuiſing, complotting, attempting, proceeding, and executing, of this their wilfull cruell and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Murther, which God in his iuſtice will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſuffer to bee hid or eſcape vnpuniſhed, then <hi>Iohn Selling</hi> vpon this went into the contry to his Miſtres, and told her that he had found his Maiſters horſe in the wood néere Wimbleton afore-ſaid: but the other two, <hi>Pet</hi> and <hi>Streater,</hi> were brought before
<pb facs="tcp:18171:6"/>Sir <hi>Thomas Gardner</hi> Knight and one of his Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties iuſtice of peace and quorum in the County of Surry, by whome they were examined, and there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that they had done this cruell fact to their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, becauſe (as they ſaid) he did not loue his wife ſo well as he ought to doe, and becauſe he did not allow them meat enough, but that which I thinke moſt is to be beleeued from them is, when they did affirme they did it by the inſpiration and inſtigation of the Diuell. Then were theſe mallefactors commited to the common iayle of the white Lyon in Sowthwark, where till the ſeſſions they are to abide, then to haue the recompence of their demerrits.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I truely and faithfully ſet downe the true diſcourſe of al this horible murder, with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the takings and attaching of the murderers, wherein the blind world may perceiue to what a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate it is brought, when as a man (for the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of ſo ſmall a ſum) ſhalbe thus maſſacred and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by his owne ſeruants, whome hee beſt ſhould truſt. It is reported that <hi>Pompey</hi> (being a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then) whoſe valiant deeds had purchaſed him the name of great, <hi>Iulius Caeſar, Marke Anthony</hi> and hee contending for the Empire and domination of the whole world. Where many bloudy battels was ſought betwéene them; yet at laſt there was a truce agreed vpon for a certaine time, in the which truce theſe thrée mighty commanders did feaſt and were merry together diuers times, and being once inuited to ſup aboord of <hi>Pompeies</hi> Galley, as they were ſate, one of
<hi>Pompeies</hi> ſeruants whiſpered him in the eare, and asked him it hee would bee Maiſter of the whole
<pb facs="tcp:18171:6"/>world. <hi>Pompey</hi> fould him yes, if he knew how, then ſaid his ſeruant againe, let vs cut <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> throates, and then all the world is thine. <hi>Pompey</hi> made anſwere, thou ſhouldſt (quoth he) haue done it without my knowledge, but now it ſhal not be don, for in me it is villany, but in thee it had bin good ſeruice. Thus this Heathen man may bee a patterne to all Chriſtians, that by his example they ſhould abhor and deteſt murther, for <hi>Pompey</hi> would not baſely take away the liues of his two mighty mortall and onely enemies, although he knew the doing of it wold haue gaind him the Monarky of the whole world. What brutiſh beaſts are theſe then, that for triffles and a little curſed coyne will murder their friends? God himſelfs ſaies that bloud ſhall haue bloud, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſheddeth mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed, yet notwithſtanding how many horrible and execrable cruelties are committed daily by man, on man, that one diuell will not deale ſo diueliſhly with another as men will doe with men. What numbers haue béene deſperately ſtabd for taking the wall, of theſe Roaring boyes of the damned crue? (as they are fittly tearmed) how many haue bin kild for refuſing to drinke their friends, miſtris or ſome-times their whores healths? The numbers are numberies, and therefore I will let them alone vnnumbered. The God of mercy and peace, iudue the harts of men with feare of thy great and glorious name, with loue and brotherly affection one toward another, that they may all with one minde in vnity worſhip thée that art their good and merciful creator, preſeruer &amp; defender: Throgh <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> thy ſonne our alone and onely
<pb facs="tcp:18171:7"/>Sauiour and Redéemer, to whom, with thée and the holy and bleſſed ſpirit be aſcribed and rendred all honor, glory, might, maieſty, dominton and thankſgiuing of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells both now and for euer more. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18171:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
